<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
<herd>sci-physics</herd>
<longdescription lang="en">
  ROOT Object Oriented Technologies is an object oriented data
  analysis framework written in C++ by the CERN. Widely used in
  high energy physics, but also in other data analysis applications. It
  contains the CINT C/C++ interpreter and many classes such as
  statistics, serialization, optimization, linear algebra, graphics,
  GUI toolkit, and a complete visualization framework.
</longdescription>
<use>
  <flag name="cern">
    Builds the HBOOK input/ouput functionality. HBOOK is a histogram
    library. On ROOT versions previous to 5.20.00, it will depend
    on <pkg>sci-physics/cernlib</pkg>. On versions above, it only need
    a FORTRAN compiler.
  </flag>
  <flag name="clarens">
    Builds the Clarens and PEAC plug-ins, to use in a GRID enabled
    analysis. The Clarens Grid-Enabled Web Services Framework is an
    open source portal for ubiquitous access to data and computational
    resources provided by computing grids. PEAC is an interactive
    distributed analysis framework that uses Clarens as a glue
    protocol to advertise and communicate amongst SAM, Global Manager
    (GM), Local Manager (LM), DCache, and PROOF services.
    It doesn't need Clarens to build, however if you want to use it,
    you will require to build Clarens and PEAC on your own, it is not
    yet in the Gentoo Portage tree. 
    See http://clarens.sourceforge.net/ for Clarens
    and http://physics.ucsd.edu/~schsu/project/peac.html for
    PEAC.
  </flag>
  <flag name="geant4">
    Builds the <pkg>sci-physics/geant</pkg> (GEANT4) navigator.    
  </flag>
  <flag name="math">
    Builds all math libraries plugins. It includes
    the <pkg>sci-libs/gsl</pkg> bindings in MathMore, the GenVector
    physical vectors package, the Minuit2 minimization library (same as
    standalone <pkg>sci-libs/minuit</pkg>), the RooFit toolkit for
    distribution modeling, and the Universal Non-Uniform RANdom number
    generators (UNURAN) library.
  </flag>
  <flag name="pythia6">
    Builds the interface to Pythia-6 (<pkg>sci-physics/pythia</pkg>)
    high energy physics generation events library.
  </flag>
  <flag name="pythia8">
    Builds the interface to Pythia-8 (<pkg>sci-physics/pythia</pkg>)
    high energy physics generation events library.
  </flag>
  <flag name="reflex">
    Builds the reflection database for the C++ interpretor.
  </flag>
  <flag name="xrootd">
    Builds the xrootd low latency file server. For more on the eXtended Request
    Daemon (xrd) and associated software, please see
    http://xrootd.slac.stanford.edu.
  </flag>
</use>
</pkgmetadata>
