<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
  <maintainer type="person">
    <email>cjk34@cam.ac.uk</email>
  </maintainer>
  <maintainer type="project">
    <email>sci@gentoo.org</email>
    <name>Gentoo Science Project</name>
  </maintainer>
  <longdescription lang="en">
  Quantitative estimate of elemental composition by spectroscopic and imaging
  techniques using X-ray fluorescence requires the availability of accurate data
  of X-ray interaction with matter. Although a wide number of computer codes
  and data sets are reported in literature, none of them is presented in the
  form of freely available library functions which can be easily included in
  software applications for X-ray fluorescence. This work presents a compilation
  of data sets from different published works and an xraylib interface in the
  form of callable functions. Although the target applications are on X-ray
  fluorescence, cross sections of interactions like photoionization, coherent
  scattering and Compton scattering, as well as form factors and anomalous
  scattering functions, are also available.

  xraylib provides access to some of the most respected databases of physical
  data in the field of x-rays. The core of xraylib is a library, written in ANSI
  C, containing over 40 functions to be used to retrieve data from these
  databases. This C library can be directly linked with any program written in
  C, C++ or Objective-C. Furthermore, the xraylib package contains bindings to
  several popular programming languages: Fortran 2003, Perl, Python, Java, IDL,
  Lua and .NET, as well as a command-line utility which can be used as a
  pocket-calculator. Although not officially supported, xraylib has been
  reported to be useable from within Matlab and LabView.
  
  Reference: T. Schoonjans, A. Brunetti, B. Golosio, M. Sanchez del Rio, 
  V. A. Solé, C. Ferrero and L. Vincze, "The xraylib library for X-ray--matter 
  interactions. Recent developments", Spectrochimica Acta B 66 (2011) 776-784 
  ( doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sab.2011.09.011 )
  </longdescription>
  <use>
  </use>
  <upstream>
    <remote-id type="github">tschoonj/xraylib</remote-id>
  </upstream>
</pkgmetadata>
