<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/doc/en/" lang="en">

  <title>Contributing to the Scientific Project</title>

  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="bicatali@gentoo.org">Sébastien Fabbro</mail>
    <!-- others add your name here -->
  </author>

  <abstract>
    This document provides information on how one can get involved and 
    help out with the Gentoo Scientific Project
  </abstract>

  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
  <license/>

  <version>0.1</version>
  <date>2009-01-21</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          This document aims to provide information on how one can get
          involved and help out with the Gentoo Scientific Project.
	  Scientific packages are very diverse and many of us want our
          pet application in the main tree for easy installation. Due to
          the small size of our team, we can not implement all of
          them, so we really appreciate any contribution.
        </p>
	<p>
	  There are few obvious areas where one can help as we
	  describe below. The Scientific Project tends to set strong
	  requirements on testing, especially on core packages.
	  Comments, thoughts, and feedback is greatly welcomed!
	</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Bugs</title>
    <section>
      <title>Reporting</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          All good software has bugs. They are too many combinations of
          compilers, USE flags and versions to test them all. So if
          you find the time to report them, we would love to hear
          about it. We have the standard bugzilla system for
          this. Don't be afraid of all these fields to fill in, it's
          not that bad!
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Resolving</title>
      <body>
        <p>
	  The Scientific Team in Gentoo has always had a high number of
	  bugs. Fortunately, many of them are new packages. Any help in resolving
	  issues, improving submitted ebuilds is greatly appreciated.
        </p>
        <p>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/2qxmvu">Bugs for the Scientific Team.</uri>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/2nm6ag">Bugs for the Biology Team.</uri>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/368f2d">Bugs for the Chemistry Team.</uri>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/2lknlo">Bugs for the Electronics Team.</uri>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/2pcntk">Bugs for the Mathematics Team.</uri>
	  <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/3789aa">Bugs for the Physics Team.</uri>
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Writing ebuilds</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
	  You don't see your application in the main tree or in the
	  overlays and you don't want to wait for someone else to
	  create the ebuilds? The most obvious solution is to develop
	  your own ebuilds. If you do so, it's always nice to share
	  them. You can post them to our bugzilla system and then one
	  of our devs will comment out. The <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/sunrise">sunrise
	  overlay</uri> allows you more directly to commit your
	  ebuilds if you don't want to wait for science access.
	</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Communication</title>
    <section>
      <title>Mailing List</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Join our
          <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml"> gentoo-science mailing list
          </uri> and asking/answering questions. 
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>IRC</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Meet some of us in #gentoo-science. It is a fairly quiet
          channel, but slowly growing and we are responsive. We can
          answer your questions, help you developing your ebuilds,
          share ideas, etc...
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
      <title>Direct emails</title>
      <body>
        <p>
	  If you feel your questions are more private and don't need
	  to be known from the rest of the world, you can always
	  directly send an email to our developers
	  listed <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/proj/science/index.xml">here</uri>
	  and the listed sub-projects. If you want to mail all of us, send a mail to the herd.
        </p>
      </body>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Writing Documentation</title>
      <body>
	<section>
          <p>
	    You may not be interested in fixing ebuilds and testing
	    packages, but want to share your knowledge about some
	    software, configuration or tips and tricks. The best way to
	    do this is to write some documentation. You can even write
	    official Gentoo documentation such as our
	    <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/proj/science/blas-lapack.xml">blas/lapack
	      guide</uri>.
	  </p>
	</section>
      </body>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Seriously getting involved</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          If you would like to join our team of volunteers and become
          an official Gentoo Developer, show activity in anywhere you
          can: bugzilla, overlays, mailing lists, irc, forums,...
	  Please refer to
	  <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml?part=1&amp;chap=2">
	  Becoming a Developer</uri> in the
	  <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml">
	  Gentoo Developer Handbook</uri>.
        </p>
	<p> 
	  Benefits are huge :-) :
          <dl>
            <dd>
              <ul>
		<li>Receive a warm welcome from us</li>
		<li>Impress your geek friends</li>
		<!--<li>Loose your social life, but</li>-->
		<li>Get a free beer first time we meet in person!</li>
              </ul>
            </dd>
          </dl>	  
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</guide>
